Register of the Štefan Osuský Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Subject File, 1910-1992. (Box 89-102)
  - Czechoslovakia
    - Foreign relations
      - Poland (Folder 93: 6-7)
      - United States (Folder 93: 8)
    - Government-in-Exile, Great Britain (Folder 93: 9)
    - History
      - 1918-1938 (Folder 93: 10-12)
      - 1938-1945 (Folder 93: 13-17)
      - 1945-1992 (Folder 93: 18-19)
    - Politics and government (Folder 93: 20-21)
    - Social conditions (Folder 93: 22)
    - Transportation (Folder 93: 23)
  - Czechoslovakia. Armada
    - France (Folder 93: 24-26)
    - Great Britain (Box-folder 94: 1)
    - Poland (Folder 94: 2-3)
  - Czechoslovakia. Československá tisková kancelář, Prague (ČTK). Reports by correspondents.
    - 1939 (Folder 94: 4)
    - 1940 (Folder 94: 5-6)
  - Czechoslovakia. Ministerstvo financi (Ministry of Finance) (Folder 94: 7)
  - Czechoslovakia. Ministerstvo národní obrany (Ministry of National Defense) (Folder 94: 8)
  - Czechoslovakia. Ministerstvo vnitra (Ministry of the Interior) (Box-folder 95: 1-4)
  - Czechoslovakia. Ministerstvo zahraničních věcí (Ministry of Foreign Affairs) (Folder 95: 5)
  - Czechs - Ethnic identity (Folder 95: 6)
  - Czechs - France (Folder 95: 7-8)
  - Czechs - United States (Folder 95: 9-10)
  - Dachau (Germany: Concentration camp). Reports by former inmates (Box-folder 96: 1)
  - Davies, Lord (Folder 96: 2)
  - Depeche Czechopress de New York (Folder 96: 3)
  - Diplomats - Slovakia (Folder 96: 4)
  - Doumer, Paul (Folder 96: 5)
  - Eberl, M. (Folder 96: 6)
  - Europe - Economic conditions, 1918-1945 (Folder 96: 7)
  - Europe - Economic conditions, 1945- (Folder 96: 8-9)
  - Europe, Central., See also Hitler, Adolf (Folder 96: 10-14)
  - Europe, Western (Folder 96: 15)
  - European Movement. Central and Eastern European Commission (Folder 96: 16-17)
  - Fecamp (Radio station), Paris (Folder 96: 18)
  - Federal government - Germany (Folder 96: 19)
  - Four Power Pact (1933). (Folder 96: 20)
    Includes text of the "Pacte des Quatre Grandes Puissances" and "Projet de Pacte d'Entente et de Collaboration," and notes by Osuský
  - France
    - Foreign Relations - Soviet Union (Folder 96: 21)
    - History - German occupation, 1940-1945 (Folder 96: 22)
    - Politics and government - 1914-1940 (Folder 96: 23)
  - Frank, Karl Herman (Folder 96: 24)
  - Friends of the Polish-Czechoslovak Union. (Folder 96: 25)
    Includes speeches of Jan Sparta and Jan Jaworski
  - Gaulle, Charles de (Box-folder 97: 1)
  - Germany
    - Economic conditions (Folder 97: 2)
    - Foreign relations
      - Czechoslovakia (Folder 97: 3)
      - Poland (Folder 97: 4)
      - Russia (Folder 97: 5)
    - History - 1933-1945., See also World War, 1939-1945 - Atrocities (Folder 97: 6-7)
  - Great Britain
    - Economic conditions (Folder 97: 8-9)
    - Foreign relations
      - France (Folder 97: 10)
      - United States (Folder 97: 11)
  - Greif, Henri (Folder 97: 12)
  - Hitler, Adolf (Folder 97: 13)
  - Hodža, Milan (Folder 97: 14)
  - Hungarian Information Service (Folder 97: 15)
  - Hungary., See also Allied and Associated Powers (1914-1920) and League of Nations. (Folder 97: 16)
    Includes memorandum of Hungarian National Council on forced labor
  - L'indepéndance tchécoslovaque (Československá samostatnost) (Folder 97: 17)
  - Institut d'Etudes Européennes (Folder 97: 18)
  - Insurance - Czechoslovakia (Folder 97: 19-20)
  - International Labor Office, Geneva (Box-folder 98: 1)
  - International Peasant Union (Folder 98: 2)
  - International Platform Association (Folder 98: 3)
  - International Refugee Organization (Folder 98: 4)
  - Justh, Ivan de (Folder 98: 5)
  - Kellogg-Briand Pact (1928) (Pacte de Paris) (Folder 98: 6)
  - Kotrchová, Helena Ludmila (Folder 98: 7)
  - Kožíšek, Adelaida (Folder 98: 8)
  - Kratzau (Poland: Concentration camp) (Folder 98: 9)
  - Little Entente, 1920-1939 (Folder 98: 10-11)
  - Machine-guns - 12mm VV 2K 395 (Folder 98: 12)
  - Machine-tools - LMG-ZGB.57 (Folder 98: 13)
  - Majdanek (Poland: Concentration camp). Reports by former inmates (Folder 98: 14)
  - Majtan, Imrich (Folder 98: 15)
  - Majtan, Magdalena (Folder 98: 16)
  - Masaryk, Jan (Folder 98: 17)
  - Masaryk, T. G. (Tomáš Garrique) (Folder 98: 18-19)
  - Metz-Wappingen (France: Concentration camp). Reports by former inmates (Folder 98: 20)
  - Middle-Zone Association (Folder 98: 21)
  - Moscow Conference (1943) (Folder 98: 22)
  - Munich Four-Power Agreement, 1938
    - General. (Folder 99: 1-2)
      Including an article by J. W. Brugel, "München 1938 - Ein fatales Symbol"
    - Bonnet, Georges, "Les Sudètes avant Munich" (Folder 99: 3)
    - Henriot, Philippe, "La Quinzaine de Munich" (Folder 99: 4)
    - Nečas, Jaromír, "Remarks About the Political Events Before and After Munich" (Folder 99: 5)
    - Ripka, Hubert, "Trouble Among Czechs," 1940 August 15 (Folder 99: 6)
    - Saint-Martial, Raoul, "Pourquoi Munich en 1938 et la guerre en 1939: Georges Bonnet l'explique dans ses 'Mémoires'" (Folder 99: 7)
    - Szalatnay-Stacho, Benjamin, "Prelude to the Red Putsch" (Folder 99: 8)
    - Schwartz, František, "Czechoslovakia, Russia, and Central Europe" (Folder 99: 9)
    - Unidentified, "Zpráva vyslance Dra Mastného o průběhu zasedání Mezinárodního komitétu pro provedení Mnichovské dohody z 20. zaří 1938" (Folder 99: 10)
  - Naarden Committee (Folder 99: 11)
  - National City Bank of New York (Folder 99: 12)
  - New Commonwealth Institute, Oxford. (Folder 99: 13-14)
    Includes issues of New Commonwealth Quarterly
  - North Atlantic Treaty Organization - Parliamentarians' Conference - Periodicals (Folder 99: 15)
  - Nouveau Départ (German social-democratic group) (Folder 99: 16)
  - Nuclear energy - Czechoslovakia (Folder 99: 17)
  - Poetry (Folder 99: 18)
  - Poláková Emilia (Folder 99: 19)
  - Poland
    - General (Folder 99: 20-23)
    - Boundaries - Soviet Union (Folder 99: 24)
    - Foreign relations
      - Czechoslovakia., See Czechoslovakia - Foreign relations
      - Germany (Folder 99: 25)
      - Soviet Union (Folder 99: 26)
  - Polish-Czech-Slovak Circle of Cultural Collaboration (Folder 99: 27)
  - Polish-Czechoslovak Union (Proposed)., See Czechoslovak-Polish Union (Proposed)
  - Press and publications excerpts, 1939-1943 (Folder 99: 28)
  - Propaganda, Czechoslovak (Box 100)
    - General (Folder 100: 1)
    - France (Folder 100: 2)
  - Radiophonic Centre of Social and International Education Based Upon Christian Ideals, Proposed creation of (Folder 100: 3)
  - Ravensbruck (Germany: Concentration camp). Reports by former inmates (Folder 100: 4)
  - Refugees, Jewish (Folder 100: 5)
  - Ribbentrop, Joachim von (Folder 100: 6)
  - Ripka, Hubert (Folder 100: 7)
  - Romania (Folder 100: 8-9)
  - Romanian Democratic Committee, London (Folder 100: 10)
  - Romanian National Council (Folder 100: 11)
  - Rosůlková, Mary (Folder 100: 12)
  - Roumanian News Survey (Folder 100: 13)
  - The Royal Empire Society (Folder 100: 14)
  - Ruthenia - History. (Folder 100: 15)
    Includes a book by František Němec, The Soviet Seizure of Subcarpathian Ruthenia
  - Sdružení zaměstnanců zahraniční služby v exilu (The Union of Employees of the Foreign Service in Exile) (Folder 100: 16)
  - Security, International (London International Assembly) (Folder 100: 17)
  - Slovak League of America (Folder 100: 18)
  - Slovakia (Folder 100: 19-21)
  - Slovaks (Box 101)
    - Ethnic identity., See Czechs - Ethnic identity
    - United States (Folder 101: 1)
  - Slovaks in foreign countries (Folder 101: 2)
  - Slovenská Informačni Služba (Slovak Information Service) (Folder 101: 3)
  - Slovenská národní rada (The Slovak Council) (Folder 101: 4)
  - Slovenská národní rada v Paříži (Slovak National Council in Paris) (Folder 101: 5)
  - Slovenská národní rada v zahraničí (Slovak National Council Abroad) (Folder 101: 6)
  - Soviet Union
    - Foreign relations
      - Germany (Folder 101: 7)
      - France., See France - Foreign relations
    - History (Folder 101: 8)
    - Publications. (Folder 101: 9)
      Includes issues of Soviet War News
    - Social conditions, 1953-1985 (Folder 101: 10)
  - Stálá Konference Slovenských Demokratických Exulantov (Permanent Conference of Slovak Democratic Exiles) (Folder 101: 11)
  - Sudeten Social Democratic Party (Folder 101: 12)
  - Světový kongres Slováků (Slovak World Congress) (Folder 101: 13-14)
  - Szalatnay-Stacho, Benjamin. (Folder 101: 15)
    Includes documents of the Czechoslovak Embassy in Cairo, Egypt, describing events happening after the German occupation of Czechoslovakia
  - Topical Surveys Limited (Folder 101: 16)
  - Union Interparlementaire (Folder 101: 17)
  - United Nations
    - Human Rights (Folder 101: 18)
    - Forced Labor (Folder 101: 19)
    - Security Council (Folder 101: 20)
  - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (Folder 101: 21)
  - Wilson, Woodrow (Box-folder 102: 1)
  - Winternitz, Josef (Folder 102: 2)
  - World Council of Churches
    - Clippings (Folder 102: 3-4)
    - Correspondence regarding the presence of Josef Hromádka, delegate of the Evangelical Church of Czech Brethren from communist Czechoslovakia, at the Second Assembly at Evanston, Illinois, 1954 (Folder 102: 5)
    - Notes by Osuský (Folder 102: 6)
  - World War, 1939-1945
    - General (Folder 102: 7-8)
    - Atrocities (Folder 102: 9)
    - Causes (Folder 102: 10)
  - Yugoslavia (Folder 102: 11)
  - Ziegenhain (Germany: Concentration camp) (Folder 102: 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 102: 13-15)
- Printed Matter, 1920-1979. (Box 103-119)
  Bulletins, clippings, newsletters, pamphlets, serial issues, and miscellany, relating mainly to Europe, before and after World War II, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General - Bulletins, newsletters, pamphlets, serial issues, and miscellany
  - Clippings (Box 106)
    - General (Folder 106: 1-3)
    - General (Box-folder 107: 1-2)
    - General (Box-folder 108: 1-3)
    - General (Box-folder 109: 1-2)
    - Czechoslovak press, 1929 (Box-folder 110: 1)
    - Czechoslovaks in France, 1929 (Folder 110: 2-3)
    - French press, 1929-1930 (Box 111-113)
    - Hungarian press, 1929-1930 (Box 114-116)
    - Hungarian press, 1930 (Box-folder 117: 1)
    - United States, 1945 (Folder 117: 2)
    - World War, 1939-1945 (Folder 117: 3)
  - Volumes of printed copies of treaties among the Allied Powers, 1918-1920 (Box 118-119)
- Restricted Series, 1939-1942. (Box 120)
  Originals in fragile condition of Osuský's statement regarding Beneš's authoritative regime, original of Osuský's holograph "Moja odpověd Ripkovi a Klecandovi," 1942 March 18, and originals of handwritten minutes of meetings on November 7 and 9, 1939, copies of which are in Career File/ Czechoslovakia. Vyslanectví (France)
- Memorabilia, 1940-1942. (Box 121)
  Two stamps used by Štefan Osuský when Minister of State of the Czechoslovak Government-in-Exile
- Card File, n.d. (Box 122-123)
  Names with addresses and telephone numbers
- Oversize File, 1928-1951. (Box 124-125)
  Album containing letters to Štefan Osuský from prominent diplomats and statesmen; maps of Central Europe in 1938, including the map of the Protektorate of Bohemia and Moravia, Carpathian Russia, France, Hungary, and Poland; and photostatic copies of New Yorkský Denník editorials attacking Osuský
  - Album containing letters to Š. Osuský from prominent diplomats and statesmen, 1928
  - Maps depicting Central Europe in 1938, including the map of the Protektorate of Bohemia and Moravia, Carpathian Russia, France, Hungary, and Poland (Box 125)
  - Photostatic copies of New Yorkský Denník editorials attacking Osuský, 1951
- Photographs, 1918-1957. (Box 126-128)
  182 prints depicting Štefan Osuský in various stages of his career, his family, World War II German atrocities and destruction in France, Charles de Gaulle, and other miscellaneous photographs
  - 37 prints collected by Osuský while Czech Ambassador to Great Britain and France, 1918-1940 (Folder 126: 1)
  - 11 prints depicting World War II German atrocities and destruction in France (Folder 126: 2)
  - 28 prints depicting Osuský in various stages of his career, 1919-1940 (Folder 126: 3)
  - 10 prints depicting Osuský's wife and son, 1920-1945 (Folder 126: 4)
  - 20 prints depicting Osuský's wife and two daughters, 1920-1945 (Folder 126: 5)
  - 1 print depicting Osuský refusing to surrender the Czechoslovak Legation to the Germans, 1939 March 16 (Folder 126: 6)
  - 8 prints depicting Osuský at the International Congress of Jurists in West Berlin, 1952 July 25-August 1 (Folder 126: 7)
  - 9 prints depicting members of the International Commission of Jurists at a Congress in Athens, 1955 June 13-20 (Folder 126: 8)
  - 1 print depicting Osuský at the Assembly of Captive European Nations, Strasbourg, 1957 (Folder 126: 9)
  - 1 print depicting Charles de Gaulle, with an explanatory note by Štefan F. Osuský, n.d. (Folder 126: 10)
  - 2 prints depicting Pavla Osuská with J. Kirschbaum, J. Mikus, and R. Frastacky at the Slovak World Congress, Toronto, 1971 (Folder 126: 11)
  - 13 prints depicting a monument at Darney, France, n.d. (Folder 126: 12)
  - 1 print depicting the Czechoslovak Consulate in Istanbul with nazi flag, 1939 (Folder 126: 13)
  - 1 print depicting the musician Jan Horáček, n.d. (Folder 126: 14)
  - 2 prints depicting Michal Samichrast, n.d. (Folder 126: 15)
  - 3 prints depicting Jan Tříska, n.d. (Folder 126: 16)
  - Album containing 33 prints depicting Osuský's visit to Litomyšl, Czechoslovakia, 1935 March 26-27 (Box 127)
  - 1 oversize print depicting Osuský at the Council of Free Czechoslovakia dinner, 1952 July 4 (Box 128)
- Incremental Materials (Box 129-133)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu